<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Making sense of related things!</title>
    <link>https://vjd.github.io/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Making sense of related things!</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2016, Vijay Ivaturi; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 14:20:19 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vjd.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Source in Pharmacometrics - ACoP7</title>
      <link>https://vjd.github.io/blog/openpmx/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 14:20:19 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vjd.github.io/blog/openpmx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 7&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; American Confernce in Pharmacometrics was held in Seattle, Washington from October 23 - 27, 2016. On the last day of the conference, there was a session named - &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;An Overview of Consortia and Open-Source Approaches to Quantitative Drug Development Tools&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This was the first time in my short experience in this field that there has been a discussion on the concept of &amp;ldquo;sharing&amp;rdquo; in pharmacometrics. It was bold, new and exciting to see initiatives being taken in our community towards being more collaborative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the list of speakers and topic session in the conference program page &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acop7.org/conference-program&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In the spirit of the topic, all the speakers decided to share their presentations and collaboratively work in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/csjf7/&#34;&gt;Open Science Framework&lt;/a&gt; (you need to sign up to the website to use it). All presentations made there will be posted here eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to summarize to the best of my ability, the overall message of that session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was a clear understanding that there needs to be a shift in the culture of doing science in pharmacometrics to be more open and collaborative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was renewed enthusiasm to work on grander challenges in a consortia setting. Many different consortia were introduced and some of them are listed here:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C-Path Initiative - develops models in consortia for Alzheimers, TB and Polycystic Kidney Disease&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantitative Systems Pharmacology (QSP) consortia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Right Dose Consortia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NeuroD Community of Practice under the C-Path initiatives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was discussion on the opportunities that we as a community have to influence precision dosing in the clinic and not just to influence drug development projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A common interest towards crowdsourced incentive based solutions to

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert published literature models into R based models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submit these R based models to the DDMore Model Repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a crowdsourced meta analysis database that allows micro-contributions from researchers all around the world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop an incentive platform to solve grand challenges in the quantitative clinical drug development and clinical therapeutics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop training material that are freely accessible to the community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new R-based non-linear mixed effect modeling engine called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nlmixrdevelopment/nlmixr&#34;&gt;nlmixr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drive towards pre-print publications using the [bioarxiv]() platform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most important aspect - there was huge shout out to the champions and their open source tools that are already available in pharmacometrics. The banner image is a timeline and list of the many open source tools available in pharmacometrics as of today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of enthusiasm at the end of the session about the prospects of an open and collaborative community in pharmacometrics. One of the ideas that was a result of this session is the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Osmosis Project&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; that stands for Open Source Modeling and Simulation Solutions, a term coined by Marc Gastonguay of &lt;a href=&#34;http://metrumrg.com/index.html&#34;&gt;Metrum Institute&lt;/a&gt;. The project will work closely with the excellent efforts of the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ddmore.eu/&#34;&gt;DDMore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; consortium and its various aspects. More details will follow up in subsequent posts. Keep an eye out!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Now?</title>
      <link>https://vjd.github.io/blog/whynow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 14:19:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vjd.github.io/blog/whynow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am flying back to Baltimore after attending the Singularity conference on &lt;a href=&#34;http://exponentialmedicine.com/&#34;&gt;Exponential Medicine&lt;/a&gt; at the beautiful Hotel Del Cornado in San Diego. I am pretty impressed with myself that I am sitting calm and writing instead of bouncing around in the plane like flubber - optimistic about the future, excited about the opportunities, thankful to have met some extraordinary people and developed some life-long relationships with peers in different walks of life. The reason I am able to sit calm is because all this excitement has thrown me into self-reflection mode. What have I done so far, what am I doing now and what lies for me in the future. Note that the use of &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;me&amp;rdquo; is only in the context of making my useful out there in this world of opportunities and enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been excited and optimistic for a long time now, but never formulated my thoughts, never gave them structure and it was all talking. I am writing now in a hope to achieve a few things -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document my thoughts so that the future me can look back at the present and past me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give myself a direction from my current vantage point by looking at how can I make a difference, even if it is a small one - tangible ones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most importantly, achieve/implement actionable items by following up on what I write, as it is much easier to slip away when you talk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have any set of specific topics. They will probably be based on the what I am doing at that specific time. I have been heavily influenced by great role models that I will bring up often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give me a shout out if you don&amp;rsquo;t hear from me here.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>